<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- generator="FeedCreator 1.7.2-ppt (info@mypapit.net)" -->
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title></title>
        <description>non-corporate news</description>
        <link>http://fivefilters.org</link>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2009 15:39:08 +0100</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>FeedCreator 1.7.2-ppt (info@mypapit.net)</generator>

        <item>
            <title>AN EYE FOR AN EYELASH: THE GAZA MASSACRE</title>
            <link>http://www.medialens.org/alerts/09/090112_an_eye_for.php</link>
            <description>&lt;td width=&quot;100%&quot; class=&quot;content&quot; id=&quot;content&quot;&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;date&quot;&gt;January 12, 2009&lt;/span&gt; 
    &lt;!--StartFragment --&gt;

    &lt;h1&gt;AN EYE FOR AN EYELASH: THE GAZA MASSACRE&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On March 24, 1999, an emotional Tony Blair appealed to the House of Commons and   to the people of Britain: &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;We must act to save thousands of innocent   men, women and children from humanitarian catastrophe.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Blair described   the emergency:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;Let me give the House an indication of the scale of what   is happening: a quarter of a million Kosovars, more than 10 per cent of the   population, are now homeless as a result of repression by Serb forces... Since   last summer 2000 people have died.&quot; (Blair: 'We must act - to save thousands of   innocent men, women and children,' The Guardian, March 23, 1999; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/Kosovo/Story/0,,209876,00.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.guardian.co.uk/Kosovo/ Story/0,,209876,00.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Not   even Blair claimed all the killings had been on one side. George Robertson, the   UK Defence Secretary at the time of the crisis, testified before the House of   Commons that until mid-January 1999, &quot;the Kosovo Liberation Army [KLA] was   responsible for more deaths in Kosovo than the Serbian authorities had been&quot;.   (Quoted, Noam Chomsky, Hegemony or Survival, Routledge, 2003, p.56)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      The   Guardian rallied to Blair's cause:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The only honorable course for Europe   and America is to use military force to try to protect the people of Kosovo...   If we do not act at all, or if there is a limited bombing campaign which still   fails to change Milosevic's mind, what is likely to be Kosovo's future?&quot;   (Leader, 'The sad need for force, Kosovo must be saved,' The Guardian, March 23,   1999)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;The following day, NATO began its 78-day blitz of Serbia. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Ten years later and almost one-half of the 2,000 death toll that so   horrified Blair and the Guardian in 1999 has been reached by the Israeli Defence   Force (IDF) in its massacre of 890 Palestinians in just over two weeks. Some   3,800 more have been wounded. The current slaughter is far more one-sided than   Kosovo. There have so far been 3 Israeli civilian deaths and 10 soldiers killed:   4 of these were victims of their own 'friendly fire'. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      KLA attacks did   nothing to temper media outrage at the spectacle of the Serbian state attacking   tiny Kosovo. The focus was on Serbian &quot;massacres&quot; and &quot;genocide&quot;. The Observer   wrote of the alleged killing of 45 Albanian civilians in Racak by Serb armed   forces on January 16, 1999:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;History will judge that the defining moment   for the international community took place on 16 January this year... Albanians   returning after an attack by Serb security forces discovered the bodies of men   they had left behind to look after the houses.&quot; (Peter Beaumont, Justin Brown,   John Hooper, Helena Smith and Ed Vulliamy, 'Hi-tech war and primitive slaughter   - Slobodan Milosevic is fighting on two fronts,' The Observer, March 28,   1999)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Serb forces, the Observer wrote, were &quot;pursuing their own version   of a Balkan Final Solution&quot;. (Ibid.)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      In 1999, British and American media   were full of talk of &quot;genocide&quot; in Kosovo. A Nexis database search showed that   between 1998-1999 the Los Angeles Times, New York Times, Washington Post,   Newsweek and Time used &quot;genocide&quot; 220 times to describe Serb actions in Kosovo.   (Email from Edward Herman to Media Lens, August 27, 2002)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      We have found   no examples of a British journalist describing Israeli actions as &quot;genocidal&quot;   over the last month. Daily Mail columnist Melanie Phillips made rare use of the   word on January 5:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;Many others also share the view that Israel is in the   wrong. So why is a country [Israel] under attack from genocidal fanatics   pilloried for defending its citizens against slaughter?&quot; (Phillips, 'Yes, this   war is terrible. But the alternative was worse - for us all,' Daily Mail,   January 5, 2009)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Israel's massacre is presented as a &quot;war&quot;, as a &quot;Gaza   conflict&quot; between two sides engaged in &quot;fighting&quot;. This is the standard fiction,   as Tim Llewellyn, the BBC's former Middle East Correspondent, noted five years   ago:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&quot;In the news reporting of the domestic BBC TV bulletins, 'balance',   the BBC's crudely applied device for avoiding trouble, means that Israel's   lethal modern army is one force, the Palestinians, with their rifles and   home-made bombs, the other 'force': two sides equally strong and culpable in a   difficult dispute, it is implied, that could easily be sorted out if extremists   on both sides would see reason and the leaders do as instructed by   Washington...&quot; (Llewellyn, '&lt;a href=&quot;/alerts/ 04/040115_Ducking_Palestine_1.HTM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Why the BBC Ducks the Palestinian Story - Part 1&lt;/a&gt;,'   Media Lens, January 15, 2004)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Norwegian doctor Mads Gilbert, one of   two foreign doctors working at Gaza's biggest hospital, al-Shifa, told CBS   News:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;I've seen one military person among the hundreds that we have seen   and treated. So anyone who tries to portray this as sort of a clean war against   another army are lying. This is an all-out war against the civilian Palestinian   population in Gaza and we can prove that with the numbers.&quot; (CBS News, January   5, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://uk.youtube.com/watch?v=Ev6ojm62qwA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://uk.youtube.com /watch?v=Ev6ojm62qwA&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    
    &lt;p&gt;Even   the death toll cited above does little to communicate the true one-sidedness of   the wider violence, injustice and cruelty. One hardly knows where to begin. For   example, largely unmentioned by the media, prior to the latest invasion, 14   Israelis had been killed by mostly homemade rockets fired from Gaza over the   last seven years as against 5,000 Palestinians killed in Israeli attacks.   (Seumas Milne, 'Israel's onslaught on Gaza is a crime that cannot succeed,' The   Guardian, December 30, 2008; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2008/dec/30/israel-and-the-palestinians-middle-east&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.guardian.co.uk/ commentisfree/2008/dec/30/israel-and-the-palestinians-middle-east&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Consider the response of Blair and the Guardian to Israel's mass   killing. From Blair there is no longer talk of the need to send bombs and tanks   to save a stricken population (Blair led calls for a ground war against Serbia).   Instead:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;I think the position is that there are circumstances in which   we could get an immediate ceasefire and that's what people want to see. I think   the circumstances focus very much around clear action to cut off the supply of   arms and money from the tunnels that go from Egypt into Gaza. I think if there   were strong, clear, definitive action on that, that would give us the best   context to get an immediate ceasefire and to start to change the situation.&quot;   (Andrew Sparrow, 'Immediate Gaza ceasefire is possible, says Tony Blair,' The   Guardian, January 6, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/jan/06/israelandthepalestinians-middleeast&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.guardian.co.uk/world/ 2009/jan/06/israelandthepalestinians-middleeast&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;No   Guardian editorials have proposed a massive military assault on Israel as the   only &quot;honorable course for Europe and America&quot;. The question has not been asked:   &quot;If we do not act at all... what is likely to be Gaza's future?&quot; Instead, the   country's &quot;leading liberal newspaper&quot; is sensitive to the perspective of the   Israeli killing machine:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The ghost of Israel's humiliation at the hands   of Hezbollah in Lebanon in 2006 hangs over this enterprise and Israel will want   to exorcise it... Israel will judge the success of its operation on the extent   to which it will have depleted Hamas's command structure, as well as its ability   to launch rockets.&quot; (Leader, 'Gaza ground assault: When victory is a hollow   word,' The Guardian, January 5, 2009)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;As we will see, the claim that   Israel is working merely to smash &quot;Hamas's command structure&quot; is a classic   liberal herring.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      The Guardian's solution: &quot;There is only one way out of   the political trap which Israeli forces are now entering, and that is an   immediate ceasefire.&quot; (Ibid.)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      To be fair, a second leader did contemplate   a slap on the wrist:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;If Israel presses on regardless, it should face an   immediate suspension of all arms from the EU, as Nick Clegg, the Liberal   Democrat leader, proposes.&quot; (Leader, 'Gaza: No shelter,' The Guardian, January   7, 2009)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    
    &lt;p&gt;As ever, Israeli politicians claim to have been heroically   restraining themselves and their capacity for violence (a manifest source of   pride) in the face of endless provocation. And yet, as recently as   February-March last year 110 Palestinian civilians were killed during 'Operation   Winter Heat'. (See our earlier Media Alerts: '&lt;a href=&quot;/alerts/08/080303_israels_illegal_assault.php&quot;&gt;Israel's Illegal Assault On The   Gaza &quot;Prison&quot;&lt;/a&gt;' March 3, 2008, and '&lt;a href=&quot;/alerts/08/080311_israeli_deaths_matter.php&quot;&gt;Israeli Deaths Matter More&lt;/a&gt;,' March   11, 2008)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      This military violence is piled on   the staggering economic violence of Israel's blockade of Gaza. Prior to the   latest offensive, John Ging who runs the Gaza operations of Unrwa, the UN agency   that looks after Palestinian refugees, told the BBC last month: &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;There's   one million on food aid, including 750,000 refugees. 80% are below the poverty   line, meaning they live on less than $2 a day. Almost 100,000 jobs have gone in   the last 18 months, since the total Israeli embargo came in. [Because that   included most building materials] $93m of Unrwa construction projects, medical   centres, houses for refugees, all are stopped. 3,200 out of 3,500 Gaza   businesses have gone down in the siege.&quot; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        &quot;There's no ray of sunlight.   It's all going in the wrong direction. It's all well documented and   predictable.&quot; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

        &quot;The Quartet [of the US, UN, Russia and the EU] said a new   approach was needed for Gaza. In fact there are even stricter sanctions.&quot; (BBC   online, 'Bowen diary: The days before war,' January 10, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/7822048.stm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi /world/middle_east/7822048.stm&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;During   the ceasefire, Israel placed severe restrictions on the number of trucks allowed   to bring food, fuel, cooking-gas canisters, spare parts for water and sanitation   plants, and medical supplies to Gaza. Israeli historian, Avi Shlaim, professor   of international relations at the University of Oxford, wrote in the Guardian: &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&quot;It is difficult to see how starving and freezing the civilians of Gaza   could protect the people on the Israeli side of the border. But even if it did,   it would still be immoral, a form of collective punishment that is strictly   forbidden by international humanitarian law.&quot; (Shlaim, 'How Israel brought Gaza   to the brink of humanitarian catastrophe,' The Guardian, January 7, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/jan/07/gaza-israel-palestine&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/ 2009/jan/07/gaza-israel-palestine&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;He   added:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The Biblical injunction of an eye for an eye is savage enough.   But Israel's insane offensive against Gaza seems to follow the logic of an eye   for an eyelash.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    
    &lt;p&gt;It is the sheer cruelty of Israeli oppression that   captures the world's imagination. Or, more accurately, defies it. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;Targeting Hamas&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The corporate media has been happy to echo   the claim that Israel is &quot;targeting Hamas&quot; rather than the Palestinian people.   In reality, the Palestinian people elected Hamas as its democratic government in   2006. And it is the Palestinian people who are paying the price now. The state   of the art, US-supplied missiles, bombs and artillery shells are not being aimed   at the regular army targets for which they were designed: tanks, command posts,   trenches and bunkers. They are being fired into residential areas in one of the   world's most densely-populated strips of land. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      The white phosphorus (WP)   shells being used are incendiary airburst weapons designed to incinerate a wide   target area. The weapon has been used by US forces in their infamous &quot;shake 'n'   bake&quot; attacks on Iraqi insurgents in cities such as Fallujah. On the BBC's World   News, correspondent Ben Brown said WP shells were being used merely to   illuminate targets in Gaza. (Brown, BBC World News, January 9)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      Israel   consistently claims that 80 per cent of those killed were Hamas &quot;militants&quot;. Al   Haq, a Palestinian legal rights group, reports that in fact 80 per cent of   Palestinian fatalities have been civilians. According to figures cited by the   World Health Organisation, at least 40 per cent have been children. (Jonathan   Cook, 'Civilian death toll spurs legal action,' The National, January 9, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thenational.ae/article/20090109/FOREIGN/417838381/1002&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.thenational.ae/article/ 20090109/FOREIGN/417838381/1002&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Medicins   Sans Frontiers (MSF) characterised the death toll as reaching &quot;alarming   proportions&quot; and indicative of &quot;extreme violence indiscriminately affecting   civilians.&quot; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://reliefweb.int/rw/rwb.nsf/db900sid/TUJA-7N55DU?OpenDocument&amp;amp;rc=3&amp;amp;cc=pse&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://reliefweb.int/rw/rwb.nsf/db900sid/ TUJA-7N55DU?OpenDocument&amp;amp;rc=3&amp;amp;cc=pse&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      Claims   of careful targeting are hardly credible given that Israeli artillery shells hit   three United Nations-run schools being used as refugee centres, killing more   than 50 people. The UN had informed the Israeli military that the schools were   refugee centres - GPS coordinates were provided. Israeli forces knew what they   were attacking and they knew the centres were packed with the same families they   had previously told to leave their homes to avoid attack. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Israel   explained that Hamas fighters had been firing from within one of the schools.   When the claim became indefensible, it was quietly withdrawn in &quot;private&quot;   briefings to Westerners - a retraction barely reported anywhere. (&lt;a href=&quot;http://uk.youtube.com/watch?v=s0BRJS6WnMs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://uk.youtube.com/watch?v=s0BRJS6WnMs&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      The latest claim (Ben Brown, BBC World News, January 11) is that the   UN-run school was hit by a stray mortar round. But just prior to the launch of   the ground offensive, Israel shelled Palestine Square, Gaza City's main shopping   area, killing five Palestinians. They destroyed the American International   School. They also destroyed a mosque in Beit Hanoun during evening prayers   killing a dozen people. At least thirty civilians were killed in Zeitoun when a   house was shelled the day after Israeli forces ordered 100 Palestinians to   shelter there (Mel Frykberg, 'Israel Fighting Also The UN,' January 10, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=45364&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=45364&lt;/a&gt;).   Were these all accidents? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Haaretz reported that, in approving the ground   invasion, the Israeli government had taken into account the likely high number   of Palestinian civilian casualties. On January 9, the paper reported that Lt.   Colonel Amir, commander of a combat engineers unit, had told Israeli TV: &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;We are very violent. We are not shying away from any method of   preventing casualties among our troops.&quot; (Amos Harel and Avi Issacharoff,   'Israel's three alternatives for the future of the Gaza war,' Haaretz, January   9, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1053590.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.haaretz.com/hasen /spages/1053590.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Israeli   media have reported that their commanders are unsurprised by the heavy civilian   toll - the priority was indeed the protection of IDF soldiers:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;For us,   being cautious means being aggressive,&quot; one told Israel's Haaretz newspaper.   &quot;From the minute we entered, we've acted like we're at war. That creates   enormous damage on the ground. I just hope those who have fled the area of Gaza   City in which we are operating will describe the shock. Maybe someone there will   sober up before it continues.&quot; (Amos Harel and Avi Issacharoff, 'Using   aggressive tactics in Gaza to save soldiers' lives,' Haaretz, January 7, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1053401.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.haaretz.com/ hasen/spages/1053401.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;These   are comments which define the methods and aims indicated by the term   'terrorism'.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      On January 6, Israeli internal security minister Meir   Shitreet responded to the massive civilian casualties on BBC's   Newsnight:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The French say, 'La guerre comme la guerre'.&quot; (January 6,   2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/b00gnjlm/Newsnight_06_01_2009/&quot;&gt;http://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/ b00gnjlm/Newsnight_06_01_2009/&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;War is indeed war, but the civilian population of Gaza is not at war -   the Geneva Conventions protecting civilian life apply.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Last year,   Shitreet suggested that residential Gaza neighbourhoods from which Hassam   rockets were fired should be obliterated: &quot;any other country would have already   gone in and level [sic] the area, which is exactly what I think the IDF should   do - decide on a neighborhood in Gaza and level it.&quot; (Attila Somfalvi,   'Sheetrit: We should level Gaza neighbourhoods,' Ynet, February 10, 2008; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ynet.co.il/english/articles/0,7340,L-3504922,00.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.ynet.co.il/english/articles/0,7340,L-3504922,00.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      He   added: &quot;We should let them know 'you have to leave, this area will be taken down   tomorrow' and just take it down - that will show them we mean   business.&quot;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Using violence to show a civilian population &quot;we mean   business&quot; is, again, terrorism. Needless to say, Shitreet was advocating major   war crimes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Prime Minister Ehud Olmert has declared that Gazan civilians   should not be allowed &quot;to live normal lives&quot;; and internal security minister Avi   Dichter has previously demanded that Israel take action &quot;irrespective of the   cost to the Palestinians&quot;. (Jonathan Cook, 'Disappearing Palestine,' Zed Books,   London, 2008, p.132)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;Preparing The Propaganda For War&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Well in   advance of the invasion, Israel developed plans to counter the inevitable images   of bloodied children and tiny, dismembered bodies. Avi Pazner, Israel's former   ambassador to Italy and France, drafted in to support the propaganda component   of the offensive, commented: &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;Whenever Israel is bombing, it is hard to   explain our position to the world. But at least this time everything was ready   and in place.&quot; (Anshel Pfeffer, 'Israel claims success in the PR war,' Jewish   Chronicle, December 31, 2008; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thejc.com/articles/israel-claims-success-pr-war&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.thejc.com/articles/ israel-claims-success-pr-war&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Eight   months ago, the perfectly named National Information Directorate was formed   within the Israeli Prime Minister's Office. This is now coordinating media   operations across the various government departments. The Directorate began   preparing for a Gaza offensive some six months ago. Yarden Vatikay, director of   the National Information Directorate, told reporters: &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;One of our   lessons from the Lebanon War [2006] was that there were too many uniforms in the   coverage, and that doesn't come over very positively.&quot; &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;As a result,   there are now: &quot;Fewer military officers; more women; tightly controlled   messages; and ministers kept on a short leash.&quot; (Ibid.)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      A press centre   was set up in the Israeli town of Sderot, near the border with Gaza, so that   foreign reporters would spend as much time as possible in the main civilian area   affected by Hamas rockets.&lt;br/&gt;
   &lt;br/&gt;
      Israeli ministers have also been ordered not   to give unauthorised interviews to avoid a repeat of last year's PR disaster   when Deputy Defence Minister Matan Vilnai threatened the Palestinians with a   &quot;holocaust&quot;. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The more Qassam [rocket] fire intensifies and the rockets   reach a longer range, they will bring upon themselves a bigger shoah because we   will use all our might to defend ourselves.&quot; ('Israeli minister warns of   Palestinian &quot;holocaust&quot;,' The Guardian, February 29, 2008; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/feb/29/israelandthepalestinians1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/ 2008/feb/29/israelandthepalestinians1&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;'Shoah'   is the Hebrew word normally used to refer to the Jewish Holocaust at the hands   of the Nazis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      A key deception promoted by the National Information   Directorate involves the claim that the latest cycle of violence began when   Hamas broke a four-month ceasefire agreed last June. In fact, Israel broke the   ceasefire when it launched a raid into Gaza on November 4, killing six people.   On November 5, the Guardian reported:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;A four-month ceasefire between   Israel and Palestinian militants in Gaza was in jeopardy today after Israeli   troops killed six Hamas gunmen in a raid into the territory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

        &quot;Hamas   responded by firing a wave of rockets into southern Israel, although no one was   injured. The violence represented the most serious break in a ceasefire agreed   in mid-June, yet both sides suggested they wanted to return to atmosphere of   calm.&quot; (Rory McCarthy, 'Gaza truce broken as Israeli raid kills six Hamas   gunmen,' The Guardian, November 5, 2008; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/nov/05/israelandthepalestinians&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008 /nov/05/israelandthepalestinians&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;The   Guardian added:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;Until now it had appeared both Israel and Hamas, which   seized full control of Gaza last summer, had an interest in maintaining the   ceasefire. For Israel it has meant an end to the daily barrage of rockets   landing in southern towns, particularly Sderot.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;On December 27, at the   start of the latest attacks, Reuters reported that US Secretary of State   Condoleezza Rice had &quot;blamed Hamas for breaking a cease-fire with Israel, which   launched air strikes on Gaza killing more than 200 people.&quot; Rice   commented:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&quot;The United States strongly condemns the repeated rocket and   mortar attacks against Israel and holds Hamas responsible for breaking the   cease-fire and for the renewal of violence in Gaza.&quot; (Tabassum Zakaria, 'Rice:   Hamas broke cease-fire,' News24, December 27, 2008; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.news24.com/News24/World/News/0,,2-10-1462_2446278,00.html&quot;&gt;http://www.news24.com/News24/World/News/0,,2-10-1462_2446278,00.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Alan   Dershowitz wrote in the Telegraph on January 10:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;Hamas deliberately   broke the ceasefire by firing rockets into southern Israel from densely   populated cities, using the areas around schools and mosques as launching   points.&quot; (Dershowitz, 'Don't play into the hands of Hamas,' Daily Telegraph,   January 10, 2009)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;The BBC's version of events from January 9 was more   subtly deceptive:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The ceasefire, brokered by the Egyptians, was often   broken in practice... Events began to come to a climax after the Israelis raided   southern Gaza on 4 November 2008 to destroy smuggling tunnels.&quot; (BBC online,   January 9, 2009;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/7818022.stm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/ world/middle_east/7818022.stm&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;No mention was made of the six human lives also destroyed in the attack.   The same BBC article, &quot;Q&amp;amp;A: Gaza conflict,&quot; asked:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;What casualties   have the Hamas rockets caused? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

        &quot;Since 2001, when the rockets were first   fired, more than 8,600 have hit southern Israel, nearly 6,000 of them since   Israel withdrew from Gaza in August 2005. The rockets have killed 28 people and   injured hundreds more. In the Israeli town of Sderot near Gaza, 90% of residents   have had a missile exploding in their street or an adjacent one.&quot;   (Ibid.)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    
    &lt;p&gt;The article noted that &quot;Palestinian medical sources say that   about 700 people have been killed in Gaza during Israel's current campaign   there.&quot; Again, curiously, despite mentioning that Hamas rockets have killed 28   Israelis since 2001, the BBC made no mention of the fact that 5,000 Palestinians   had been killed by Israeli strikes over the same period prior to the current   Israeli offensive - a figure fast approaching 6,000. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;Plan Dalet - A Hidden History Of Ethnic Cleansing&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Defending the BBC's   long record of biased reporting, the BBC's Middle East editor, Jeremy Bowen,   responded: &quot;we have reported the facts about Israel's occupation many times, and   we will do so again.&quot; (Bowen, email forwarded to Media Lens, January 2,   2009)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      But the &quot;facts&quot; of the occupation are nowhere in sight. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      Unknown to most of the British public, huge numbers of Palestinians were   forced from their land when the Israeli state was formed in 1948. The Israeli   historian Ilan Papp notes that more than half of Palestine's native population,   close to 800,000 people, were uprooted and 531 villages were destroyed. (Papp,   'The Ethnic Cleansing of Palestine,' Oneworld Publications, Oxford, 2006) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      The intention of 'Plan Dalet', carried out by the military forces of   what later became Israel, was to ethnically cleanse a large part of Palestine of   hostile &quot;Arab elements&quot;. Numerous massacres occurred at Deir Yassin, Ayn   Al-Zaytun, Tantura and elsewhere. Avi Shlaim, another Israeli historian,   writes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The novelty and audacity of the plan lay in the orders to   capture Arab villages and cities, something [Jewish forces] had never attempted   before... Palestinian society disintegrated under the impact of the Jewish   military offensive that got underway in April, and the exodus of the   Palestinians was set in motion... by ordering the capture of Arab cities and the   destruction of villages, it both permitted and justified the forcible expulsion   of Arab civilians.&quot; (Shlaim, 'The Iron Wall: Israel and the Arab World,' W. W.   Norton &amp;amp; Company, New York, 2000, p.31)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Speaking in 1955, prominent   Israeli military leader and politician, Moshe Dayan, asked:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;What cause   have we to complain about their fierce hatred for us? For eight years now they   sit in their refugee camps in Gaza, and before their eyes we turn into our   homestead the land and villages in which they and their forefathers have lived.&quot;   (Quoted, ibid., p.101)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;The Palestinians were forced to live as refugees   in Lebanon, Syria, Jordan and on the West Bank (of the Jordan River) and the   Gaza Strip. A series of conflicts and, at times, outright war followed between   Israel and its Arab neighbours. During the 1967 (Six Day) War, Israel occupied   the West Bank and East Jerusalem (previously under Jordanian control), the Gaza   Strip and the Sinai peninsula (Egypt) and the Golan Heights (Syria). This   occupation brought many Palestinian refugees under Israeli military   control.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Jerusalem, a religious centre for Muslims, Jews and Christians,   became a major centre of conflict. The Israelis also built illegal settlements   in the newly occupied areas of Gaza and the West Bank and exploited natural   resources, in particular taking control of vital water resources. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Shlaim   writes that these settlements were part of a systematic policy intended to exert   strategic and military control which in this case involved, &quot;surrounding the   huge Greater Jerusalem area with two concentric circles of settlements with   access roads and military positions.&quot; (Ibid., p.582)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      The public is able   to learn almost nothing of this from media reporting, as the Glasgow University   Media Group has documented many times. In their book, Bad News From Israel, Greg   Philo and Mike Berry wrote of one study of media performance:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The lack   of historical knowledge made it very difficult for people to understand key   elements of the conflict. For example, some [viewers] had written that 'land'   was an issue but there was a great deal of confusion over what this meant.   Another participant described how his understanding included no sense of the   Palestinian case that land had been taken from them.&quot; (Philo and Berry, 'Bad   News From Israel,' Pluto Books, London, 2004, p.216)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    
    &lt;p&gt;A Media Lens reader,   Chris Newman, conducted a survey of 19 BBC online articles on the Gaza crisis on   January 5, 2009 (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medialens.org/forum/viewtopic.php?t=2918&quot;&gt;http://www.medialens.org/ forum/viewtopic.php?t=2918&lt;/a&gt;).   As examples of his analysis, he found:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      1. Mentions of refugees of 1948 or   1967, who make up the bulk of the Gaza population and are entitled to right of   return under international law - 1 mention in a side article.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      2. Mentions   of the Occupation of Gaza (as stipulated by the UN it is still occupied) - 2   mentions in a side article. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      As Newman concluded: &quot;very little context to   the foundations of Palestinian resistance is given. The UN has reported that it   is the Occupation that is the cause of the Palestinian resistance, and as such   these are extremely important points.&quot; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      It is standard media practice for   such context to be entirely absent or buried out of sight. &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;Deeper   Motives - Israel's Not-So-Hidden Agenda&lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Journalists fully accept Israel's   claims that its actions were taken to stop Hamas firing rockets into Israel from   Gaza. The media has also speculated that the goal is to restore Israel's   military 'credibility'. A Financial Times editorial observed:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The   overall aim of the politico-military establishment... appears to be re-establish   the credibility of Israel's deterrent power, lost in the 34-days' war against   Hizbollah in Lebanon in 2006, which offered a very public exhibition of the   limits to Israel's otherwise overwhelming military might. Now, Mr Barak says,   Israel is going to 'change the rules of the game'.&quot; (Editorial, 'A dangerous   gamble in Gaza,' Financial Times, January 4, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/e56ac646-da93-11dd-8c28-000077b07658.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/e56ac646-da93- 11dd-8c28-000077b07658.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;But   insightful, independent commentators have been willing to look at the deeper   issues. Nazareth-based journalist Jonathan Cook comments:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The   politicians and generals have been preparing for this attack for many months,   possibly years - a fact alone that suggests they have bigger objectives than   commonly assumed. Israel seized this particular moment - with western   politicians dozing through the holidays and a change over of administrations in   Washington - because it ensured the longest period to implement its plan without   diplomatic interference.&quot; (Cook, 'Objectives bigger than commonly assumed,' The   National, January 7, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thenational.ae/article/20090107/FOREIGN/679011682/1140&quot;&gt;http://www.thenational.ae/article/ 20090107/FOREIGN/679011682/1140&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Cook   argues that Israel's bigger objectives can be achieved whether Hamas falls or   remains, so long as it is crushed politically. But what +are+ these objectives?   And why does the corporate media have nothing to say about them?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      Avi   Shlaim observes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The declared aim of the war is to weaken Hamas and to   intensify the pressure until its leaders agree to a new ceasefire on Israel's   terms. The undeclared aim is to ensure that the Palestinians in Gaza are seen by   the world simply as a humanitarian problem and thus to derail their struggle for   independence and statehood.&quot; (Shlaim, 'How Israel brought Gaza to the brink of   humanitarian catastrophe,' The Guardian, January 7, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/jan/07/gaza-israel-palestine&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/ 2009/jan/07/gaza-israel-palestine&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    
    &lt;p&gt;Historically,   the United States - Israel's armourer and diplomatic sponsor - has played a   supporting role, belying its carefully-crafted image as a &quot;neutral broker&quot;.   Thus, the US was the only country to abstain from last week's United Nations   Security Council resolution calling for an immediate ceasefire. A BBC report   noted blandly that &quot;the US abstention weakened the impact of the vote because   Washington's support would have placed more pressure on Israel to halt its   offensive&quot;. ('Bombs hit Gaza as UN calls for truce,' January 9, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/7819371.stm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/ middle_east/7819371.stm&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      A   glimpse of the real US role, buried in almost all mainstream coverage, was   provided by Israel's Haaretz newspaper. The US ambassador to the UN, Zalmay   Khalilzad, had &quot;received explicit instructions from his superiors at the State   Department to torpedo any initiative proposed by the Arab bloc which is designed   to grant the Security Council the status of an official arbiter that will have   direct involvement with disentangling the Gaza crisis.&quot; (Shlomo Shamir, Haaretz   correspondent, and Reuters, 'U.S. to foil any Arab bid to push Security Council   resolution for Gaza cease-fire,' Haaretz, January 5, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1052887.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.haaretz.com/ hasen/spages/1052887.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Hamas   has repeatedly declared its readiness to negotiate a long-term ceasefire with   the Jewish state within its pre-1967 borders. But Israel has rejected the offer,   just as it rejected the Arab League peace plan of 2002; and just as it has   always rejected the international consensus for a peaceful solution in the   Middle East. Why? Because the threat of such 'peace offensives' would involve   unacceptable concessions and compromises. The well-known Israeli writer Amos   Elon has written of the &quot;panic and unease among our political leadership&quot; caused   by Arab peace proposals. (Cited, Noam Chomsky, 'Fateful Triangle,' Pluto Press,   London, 1999, p.75) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      The Palestinians are seen as an obstacle by Israel's   leaders; an irritant to be subjugated. Noam Chomsky   writes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;Traditionally over the years, Israel has sought to crush any   resistance to its programs of takeover of the parts of Palestine it regards as   valuable, while eliminating any hope for the indigenous population to have a   decent existence enjoying national rights.&quot; ('Chomsky on the US, Israel, and   Gaza,' January 8, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thecommentfactory.com/noam-chomsky-on-the-us-israel-and-gaza-1298&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.thecommentfactory.com /noam-chomsky-on-the-us-israel-and-gaza-1298&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;And   so, as Chomsky notes:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The key feature of the occupation has always been   humiliation: they [the Palestinians] must not be allowed to raise their heads.   The basic principle, often openly expressed, is that the 'Araboushim' - a term   that belongs with 'nigger' or 'kike' - must understand who rules this land and   who walks in it with head lowered and eyes averted.&quot; (Chomsky, 'Fateful   Triangle,' op. cit., p.489)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;The full title of Jonathan Cook's latest book   indicates the reality underpinning current Israeli policy: 'Disappearing   Palestine: Israel's experiments in human despair.' Behind &quot;a mask of false   legitimacy&quot;, Israel &quot;has carried out the destruction of Palestinian identity and   living space and the theft of resources.&quot; (Cook, 'Disappearing Palestine,'   p.70)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Veteran Israeli peace activist Uri Avnery concurs, arguing that the   Gaza blockade is &quot;a scientific experiment designed to find out how much one can   starve a population and turn its life into hell before they break.&quot; Avnery adds:   &quot;The present war is a continuation of the experiment by other means.&quot; (Uri   Avnery, 'Molten Lead in Gaza,' Counterpunch, January 2-4, 2009; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.counterpunch.org/avnery01022009.html&quot;&gt;http://www.counterpunch.org/ avnery01022009.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      Reporting   from inside Israel, Cook has carefully documented the longstanding oppression of   the 4 million Palestinians in the occupied territories of Gaza and the West   Bank, as well as the 1.2 million second-class Palestinian citizens within Israel   itself. Because of their relatively high birth rate, Palestinians are seen by   many Israelis as a &quot;demographic time-bomb&quot;; a threat to the Jewish nature of the   Israeli state. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      In 2002, General Eitan Ben Elyahu, a former head of   Israel's air force, declared on Israeli television that &quot;eventually we will have   to thin out the number of Palestinians living in the territories.&quot; (Cook, op.   cit., pp.134-135) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      This vision of ethnic cleansing would have been   familiar to David Ben-Gurion, one of the main architects of Israel and its first   prime minister. The vision is a campaign of bombing, starving and maiming to   terrorise the Palestinian population into flight; a terrible echo of 1948. The   ethnic cleansing of Palestine in 1948, was massive and brutal, but incomplete:   80 per cent not 100 per cent of the Palestinians were expelled.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      Cook   warns that the political rise of Avigdor Lieberman, an immigrant from Moldova   who leads a far-right party, is a sign of things to come. Lieberman, says Cook,   &quot;is the likely face of Israel's political future. He has been publicly   promoting, and garnering support for, the expulsion of Israel's Palestinian   minority, a policy that has been secretly formulated by more mainstream leaders   for some time.&quot; (Ibid., pp.139-140)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Israeli historian Benny Morris,   previously a liberal voice, &quot;is one of a growing number of Israelis espousing   this hardline policy of expulsion, or 'transfer' as it is more commonly, and   coyly, referred to.&quot; (Ibid., p.141)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Cook argues that Israel's real   intention is to replicate the apartheid model of South Africa; to transform   Palestinian cities into Bantustans in a sea of Israeli-dominated territory,   leaving Israeli settlers in possession of the arable land and vital water   resources. He warns:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;The apartheid model is unlikely to be the end of   the story, however... Another solution - transfer - will be needed. The Israeli   public is already being softened up, with government ministers openly   subscribing to it. Palestinians will have to be encouraged, or made, to leave   their homes and land.&quot; (Ibid., pp.149-150)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Ilan Papp notes that leading   Zionist figures have long held such views. One of them, Yossef Weitz, wrote in   1940: &quot;it is our right to transfer the Arabs&quot; and &quot;The Arabs should go!&quot; (Papp,   'The Ethnic Cleansing of Palestine,' OneWorld, Oxford, 2006, p.23) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      In   1948, David Ben-Gurion argued:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;We must use terror, assassination,   intimidation, land confiscation, and the cutting of all social services to rid   the Galilee of its Arab population.&quot; (Edward S. Herman and Grace Kwinjeh,   'Ethnic Cleansing: Constructive, Benign, and Nefarious (Kafka Era Studies, No.   1),' ZNet, August 9, 2006; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zmag.org/znet/viewArticle/3419&quot;&gt;http://www.zmag.org/znet/viewArticle/3419&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;Fifty   years later, in 1998, Ariel Sharon made the same point: &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&quot;It is the duty   of Israeli leaders to explain to public opinion, clearly and courageously, a   certain number of facts that are forgotten with time. The first of these is that   there is no Zionism, colonization or Jewish state without the eviction of the   Arabs and the expropriation of their lands.&quot; (Ibid.)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/blockquote&gt;    &lt;p&gt;On May 24, 2006,   Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Olmert told a joint session of congress that &quot;I   believed and to this day still believe, in our people's eternal and historic   right to this entire land.&quot; (Ibid.)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Disturbingly, up to 60 per cent of   Israeli Jews support schemes to encourage or force Arabs to leave both the   occupied territories and Israel. (Cook, op. cit.,   p.141)&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Edward Herman and Grace Kwinjeh point out   that Israel's brutal invasion of Lebanon in 2006 was portrayed as an act of   self-defense against a threat from Hezbollah. In fact, as Kaveh L Afrasiabi   wrote, this was a war &quot;to annex a major chunk of Lebanese territory without   necessarily saying so, under the pretext of security buffer and deterrence   against future attacks on Israel&quot;. (Quoted, Herman and Kwinjeh, op.   cit.)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      This drive to &quot;redeem the land&quot;, in Zionist parlance, requires the   forcible takeover of land in the possession of others. As such, Herman and   Kwinjeh note, it &quot;constitutes a model case of a quest for a 'Greater' entity -   here a Greater Israel - a drive which in the case of Milosevic's and the Serbs'   alleged drive for a 'Greater Serbia' was presented as a prime element of illegal   activity in the ICTY [International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia]   indictment of Milosevic.&quot; (Ibid.) &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      As Chomsky says so well, the violent   reactions of Hamas &quot;can be condemned as criminal and politically foolish, but   those who offer no alternative have no moral grounds to issue such judgments,   particularly those in the US who choose to be directly implicated in these   ongoing crimes - by their words, their actions, or their silence.&quot; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thecommentfactory.com/noam-chomsky-on-the-us-israel-and-gaza-1298&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.thecommentfactory.com /noam-chomsky-on-the-us-israel-and-gaza-1298&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      The   ongoing assault on Gaza, then, is about far more than restoring military pride,   preventing rocket attacks and crushing Hamas. It is about Israel's strategic   plan to deliver the Palestinian people to an abysmal fate in pursuit of the   Zionist dream. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      As is the case for all major US-UK allies, honest   analysis of state policy of this level of ugliness is all but unthinkable for a   mainstream corporate media that is anything but free and   independent.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;SUGGESTED ACTION &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The goal of Media Lens is to   promote rationality, compassion and respect for others. If you do write to   journalists, we strongly urge you to maintain a polite, non-aggressive and   non-abusive tone. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Write to Jeremy Bowen&lt;br/&gt;

      Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jeremy.bowen@bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;jeremy.bowen@bbc.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Write to   Helen Boaden, director of BBC News&lt;br/&gt;
      Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:helenboaden.complaints@bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;helenboaden.complaints@bbc.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      Jon   Snow, Channel 4 news presenter &lt;br/&gt;
      Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:jon.snow@itn.co.uk&quot;&gt;jon.snow@itn.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      David Mannion,   ITV news editor in chief &lt;br/&gt;

      Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:david.mannion@itn.co.uk&quot;&gt;david.mannion@itn.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      Alan   Rusbridger, editor of the Guardian &lt;br/&gt;
      Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:alan.rusbridger@guardian.co.uk&quot;&gt;alan.rusbridger@guardian.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

      Roger   Alton, editor of the Independent &lt;br/&gt;
      Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:r.alton@independent.co.uk&quot;&gt;r.alton@independent.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please   send a copy of your emails to us &lt;br/&gt;
      Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:editor@medialens.org&quot;&gt;editor@medialens.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;</description>

        </item>
        <item>
            <title>UK Indymedia - What Does The Economic Crisis Mean For The Climate ...</title>
            <link>http://www.indymedia.org.uk/en/2009/02/422410.html</link>
            <description>&lt;div class=&quot;content&quot;&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;

      &lt;a name=&quot;abstract&quot; id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We are in the middle of two crises, the climate crisis and the economic crisis. Although we we seem to treat them as separate, it can be argued that they are completely entangled. Tackling one without tackling the other is impossible and fruitless, but the connections are complex and shifting. To intervene effectively, we need to look carefully at how we think about time and change, and how we relate to markets and the state. But first, let's look at how the economic crisis arose and draw some link between this history and the problematics of climate politics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other aspects of economic crisis:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/en/regions/leedsbradford/2009/02/422101.html&quot;&gt;Leeds&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;/en/2009/01/417372.html&quot;&gt;Liverpool&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;/en/2009/02/421838.html&quot;&gt;Public services cuts&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;/en/2009/01/420514.html&quot;&gt;Evictions&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;/en/2009/02/421286.html&quot;&gt;Factory Occupations&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

          
     
      &lt;!-- media --&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;media&quot;&gt;
          
          
          
          
            &lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
              &lt;img src=&quot;/images/2009/02/422414.jpg&quot; width=&quot;483&quot; height=&quot;331&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;

            &lt;/p&gt;
          	  
        &lt;/div&gt;	 
      &lt;!-- /media --&gt;
     

    &lt;br class=&quot;contentbreak&quot; /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;articlecontent&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a name=&quot;article&quot; id=&quot;article&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

      &lt;h3&gt;The Last 60 Years&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;To understand the current economic crisis (and the collapse of what we call neo-liberalism, the most current phase of capitalism), we have to understand how it arose. And for that we have to go right back to the end of the Second World War. The post-war productivity boom was based on a deal of higher wages in return for improved productivity  those were the days when we were told youve never had it so good. But by late 1960s this period of growth was being derailed by a wave of strikes and global unrest: in the workplace there were a growing number of struggles over time &amp;amp; quality of life (rather than money), while there was an explosion of anger from those excluded from this deal (i.e. anyone who wasnt a white, skilled, male factory worker).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the face of this, the post-war settlement was killed off in the mid- to late-1970s by a capitalist counter-attack which laid the foundations for neo-liberalism. You can pick any number of key moments  the coup in Chile in 1973, the defeat of the US air traffic controllers strike in 1981, or the defeat of the miners in 1984/5 in the UK. They were all part of a much broader systematic strategy, which played out here like this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, the old centres of workers militancy (mining, manufacturing) were dismantled and outsourced to low-wage economies overseas. In the UK in 1971 over 70% of people were employed in primary industries (like mining) or manufacturing, today over 70% of workers are in the service sector.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second, the banking sector was massively deregulated. All sorts of complicated derivatives markets were created. When this started to unravel in summer 2007, it ultimately resulted in the credit crunch  because no-one knew what all these pieces of paper were really worth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under neo-liberalism, wages were driven ever downward. Many of us are have found that every pay rise weve had over the last 15 years has been below the rate of inflation. But while this boosts profits, the problem is that it keeps consumer spending (= economic growth) down. This problem was solved by extending massive consumer credit, based mostly on rising house prices. This gave us the spending power to purchase all those lovely commodities coming out of the new manufacturing centres in the Far East and elsewhere. Hence the anomaly where our living standards in the UK rose at the same time as our wages as a proportion of profits kept falling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Without primary industries or manufacturing the economy came to rely more and more on the banking and financial sector. This sector was in turn heavily reliant on rising house prices: complicated mortgage derivatives were one of the major assets held by the big banks. So when the housing bubble burst, everything started to unravel  banks teetered on the brink of collapse, credit dried up, and the economy nose-dived.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are in uncharted waters. Despite comparisons to 1929, this level of collapse is unprecedented. How things pan out is of course partly down to us. But we dont need a crystal ball to predict the storm thats coming: in the UK, were already facing redundancies, wage cuts, benefit cuts, wage cuts, public service cuts, repossessions &amp;amp; evictions. Globally, there is mass social unrest on the horizon: workers laid off from thousands of factories in China have taken to the streets; food riots exploded in over 30 countries across the globe this time last year; and in the last few months weve seen violent battles in Latvia, Bulgaria &amp;amp; Iceland, not to mention Greece, Italy and France&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;What Has All This Got To Do With Climate Change?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the 'liberal' media and in the thoughts of many, theres a shift of focus away from climate change, affecting us as citizens/campaigners/workers/claimants but also for NGOs and local and national government. Plus we now have to deal with the fact that a huge slice of public funds have been diverted into propping up financial institutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But we need to dig deeper. We talk about it as a climate crisis but from the point of view of capitalism (seen as a thing, an endlessly expanding dynamic system) its actually an energy crisis. And its an energy crisis that capital has to tackle in order to re-launch a new cycle of accumulation. This isnt something new: the idea of limits to growth were an endless headache for capital in the mid-1970s before neo-liberalism took hold and unleashed new levels of exploitation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In fact energy in its widest sense has been a permanent problem for capitalist development. Capitalism is an exploitative, ecologically destructive system but it is also incredibly dynamic. 300 years ago, when it faced down a similar twin crisis of a rebellious population and ecological crisis, its salvation was coal. Unlocking these carbon resources played a crucial role by allowing capital to substitute machinery for our labour, at a price that could sometimes be fixed years in advance and without risk of strikes, sabotage or go-slows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its impossible to think about patterns of energy consumption, and therefore about global warming, without thinking of those social relations  capitalist social relations  that have shaped those patterns. The collapse of neo-liberalism and the climate crisis are intimately linked  so much so that theyre almost impossible to separate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This isnt necessarily a bad thing, for us. At the back of much of the talk around climate change has been the idea that if we can just get people to accept the thesis of peak oil or global warming, then we will be able to magically pass into a different sort of world; as if we could switch off a carbon-based economy without also switching off the material social relations that surround it; as if the relentless drive for economic growth is some sort of mad aberration that we can turn off, or tone down. Its not. There is no accident. There are structural causes at work here: the way we reproduce ourselves socially is bound up with the way we reproduce ourselves economically and the way we reproduce ourselves ecologically. But  and this is the key thing  the global financial meltdown could lead to a recomposition of social forces that would enable the rapid switch-over we need.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To get that switch-over right, here are four related areas worth thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;1. How Do We Think About Time?&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;By this we dont simply mean the time-scales we need to think about, although they are also important. Theres a time lag in the economic crisis which mirrors the time lag in climate change&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;the first cracks in the sub-prime sector began Aug 2007 = implosion last year&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;credit crisis from last summer = redundancies &amp;amp; layoffs now&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;500bn bank bail-out last autumn = massive public sector squeeze for the foreseeable future&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This disconnection makes our responses very difficult  by the time we act, it may be too late. But theres an even more important aspect to this time lag. Neo-liberalism has been built on a massive expansion of debt. By mortgaging our futures (quite literally in the case of pensions) weve been able to put off dealing with the fact that a few are reaping massive profits on the back of our falling wages. The same deferral, the same displacement of antagonism into the future, has also been going on with climate change. However, we know that process to be non-linear: once we reach a tipping point, change will become irreversible, so that when the time comes to 'pay' we'd all be screwed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This leads into a deeper connection. Capitalist social relations are based on a particular notion of time. Capital is value in process: it has to move to remain as capital (otherwise its just money in the bank). That moving involves a calculation of investment over time  an assessment of risk and a projection from the present into the future. The interest rate, for example, is the most obvious expression of this quantitative relation between the past, the present and the future. It sets a benchmark for the rate of exploitation, the rate at which our present doing  our living labour  must be dominated by and subordinated to our past doing  our dead labour.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its hard to over-state how corrosive this notion of time is. It lies at the heart of capitalist valorisation, the immense piling-up of things, but it also lies at the heart of the production of everyday life. To paraphrase George Orwell, if you want a picture of the future, imagine a cash till ringing up a sale, forever. This is true at all levels, whether for capitals planners meeting in Davos or for us trying to make ends meet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But this is the deeper meaning of the meltdown: just like global warming, it has brought the future crashing into the present. Interest rates are now effectively below zero. We have reached a singularity. Capitals temporality depends upon a positive rate of interest, along with a positive rate of profit and a positive rate of exploitation  all that has collapsed. And just as with climate chaos, the debts are, quite literally, being called in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;2. How Do We Think About Change?&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;The word crisis has its origins in a medical term meaning turning point  the point in the course of a serious disease where a decisive change occurs, leading either to recovery or to death. So capitalism may be in crisis, neo-liberalism may be over, but that doesnt mean weve won. Far from it. Crisis is inherent to capitalism. Periodic crises allow capital to displace its limits, using them as the basis for new phases of accumulation. In that respect, its true to say that capitalism works precisely by breaking down. But thats only true in retrospect  after the resolution of the crisis. In fact crisis is mortally dangerous to capital, because it means an openness to other possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The critical instability were living through offers a chance for a phase transition, a rapid flip from one form of social organisation to another  or to many others. From capitals point of view, its exactly this sense of openness, of possibility, that needs to be closed down. At the three major summits this year (G20 in the UK in April, G8 in Italy in July, and &lt;a href=&quot;/en/actions/2009/cop15/&quot;&gt;COP15&lt;/a&gt; in Denmark in December), world leaders will be looking to contain things, to rein in our desires, and draw a line under the events of the past few months. Move along now, theres nothing to see here Every solution thats touted at these summits will also be an act of closure, an attempt to reintroduce capitalist temporality, one that sees the future rolling out inexorably from the present. In other words, get back to work: normal service will be resumed as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have to do a fine balancing act here. On the one hand, as recession deepens, well resist any measures that restrict our immediate freedoms. That might mean pushing for solutions that are slightly less damaging, and which may therefore help capitalism off its sickbed. Individually we may accept pay cuts rather than risk redundancies (although historically one hasnt ruled out the other). Similarly, the catastrophic build-up of greenhouse gases means that we need to act quickly and decisively.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But on the other hand our greatest chance of something different lies in keeping the crisis ongoing, in keeping the future &lt;i&gt;open&lt;/i&gt;. So we also have to resist the pressure from capitals planners for a quick fix, whether at the G20 or at Copenhagen. As soon as crises are solved, our room for manoeuvre is diminished.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;3. How Do We Relate To The Market?&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;As crises are closed down, the way the question is framed moves back on to a safer terrain for capital. We drift back into its particular form of temporality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Climate change becomes a matter of carbon trading, or investment, rather than circulation of capital. It becomes a question of technical solutions and national/international policy decisions. Funnily enough, as climate change becomes the major topic at summits, it becomes fundamentally depoliticised. Its easier to debate carbon parts per million in the atmosphere, rather than ask ourselves what sort of worlds we want to live in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its the same with the financial meltdown. Since last summer, its gone from a banking crisis to a credit crunch to an economic crisis to negative economic growth to recession. For months the use of the word recession was discouraged on the grounds that it would become self-fulfilling. But if theres no name to what were living through, it cant be normalised. And if its not normal, then we can behave exceptionally So its officially a Recession.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can see this move from crisis to recession in another way: a crisis &lt;i&gt;for capital&lt;/i&gt; has become a crisis &lt;i&gt;for us&lt;/i&gt;. Costs are shifted on to us. The massive bail-out of the banking system in the UK and the US is just the tip of the iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And its exactly the same with climate change. Its obvious that costs of climate change are met disproportionately by the poor: globally its the poor who are most at risk of flooding, spread of disease, crop failure, resource shortages etc. And without a structural change, the costs of alleviating climate change will also be met by the poor. Three examples: green technologies are likely to remain expensive, so the poor will be shut out and forced to use dirty energy; agrofuel schemes which are still being forcibly rolled out across the global South (and in the US) in the face of widespread opposition; increasing enclosure of common land in the name of conservation, driving people away from resources that they have traditionally worked in order to sustain themselves. And in fact, as well as excluding the poor, all three have disastrous environmental consequences&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we frame the question in this way, if we support attempts to resolve these crises through the market, and through the state, then we run the risk of engendering a green Keynesianism. In other words, a new regime of capitalist accumulation based on any combination of renewable energy, nuclear power, so-called clean coal or agrofuels. Its easy to see how this could make sense. You start off with the idea that in terms of life on earth were all in it together; but we need to save the economy first to enable us to have the resources to tackle the challenge&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In fact, far from being a problem to overcome, the hope is that climate change may actually become a primary source of revenue to solve the massive fiscal problems faced by Europe and the US (but not those of the global South). Renewable energy, for example, is a huge growth sector, where demand far outstrips supply. And according to the head of UN Climate Change Secretariat: The credit crisis can be used to make progress in a new direction, an opportunity for global green economic growth it is an opportunity to rebuild the financial system that would underpin sustainable growth  Governments now have an opportunity to create and enforce policy which stimulates private competition to fund clean industry. Or as the European commission President puts it when the EU signed a new climate change deal in December We mean business when we talk about climate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But if the key question isnt &lt;i&gt;whether&lt;/i&gt; we shift away from fossil fuels, but &lt;i&gt;how&lt;/i&gt;, then framing the answer in terms of the market and growth is a huge and explosive contradiction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem of adopting the market as a frame of reference is that capital monetizes everything, it turns everything into money. And with financialisation, that trend has become even stronger. Under neo-liberalism, one of the most important roles of the the state, locally and globally, has been to impose good governance. In other words, to reinforce the idea that every problem raised by struggles can be addressed  on &lt;i&gt;one&lt;/i&gt; condition: that we address those problems through the market. Theres a solution for everything, as long as we buy it. Or rather as long as we (meaning the worlds poor) pay for it. If neo-liberalism had a slogan, it would be stop me and buy one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ironically some of the pressure for this has come from green campaigners who have argued, correctly, that capitalism takes no account of environmental costs when calculating price. But under the dictatorship of the market, money has become the measure of all things. The market tries to make commensurable things that are incommensurable. But how can you sell the right to emit carbon? Or to poison water supplies?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This isnt simply an ethical question, one of value (as imposed by capital) against values (what we hold dear). The idea of price is also based on linear dynamics. What price can you put on something when you can no longer calculate the probable outcome? As sea levels rise, its easy to predict coastal flooding. But then theres the amount and pattern of rainfall, a probable expansion of the subtropical desert regions, Arctic shrinkage and resulting Arctic methane release, increases in the intensity of extreme weather events, changes in agricultural yields, modifications of trade routes, glacier retreat, species extinctions and changes in the ranges of disease vectors Put that in your calculator.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;4. How Do We Relate To The State?&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;With neo-liberalism in crisis, and the threat of irreversible climate change, the states role is going to become increasingly crucial. A de-carbonised global capitalism is not impossible, but it would require even higher levels of discipline. Austerity would have to be enforced on a massive scale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As we said earlier, capitalism is value in process  like a shark, it needs to keep moving or die. But this drive to self-expansion means it needs an ever-increasing energy base. Lets look at it from the perspective of capitalism. The logic of capitalist growth is that it will always seek to externalise its costs. If we imagine theres a three-way relation between capital, us and the environment (although none of these three things are actually discrete), then limits enforced in one sphere re-surface as intensified exploitation in another. If capital cant rob one, it will rob the other. Leaving the coal in the hole, with no other change, means more energy sucked from our bodies. Lets not forget that the last capitalist era of renewable energy (the age of sails and windmills) was also a time of slavery, genocide and enclosures on a massive scale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are no easy answers here. The ground on which were fighting is shifting far too fast for that. But one thing to bear in mind is that movements rarely take straightforward forms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1905 the Russian revolution which threw up the first Soviets began with a small strike by typesetters at a Moscow print-works: they wanted a shorter working day, a higher rate of pay, and the right to be paid for apostrophes. In France the uprising of May 68 was sparked in part by a student protest which began in Nanterre with a fight over demand for boys to be let into girls dormitories&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week a wave of &lt;a href=&quot;/en/2009/01/417372.html&quot;&gt;wildcat strikes&lt;/a&gt; swept through UK oil refineries. They were hugely controversial, unpredictable, and came out of nowhere. Who knows their long-term meaning? And is it a coincidence that they happened in the energy sector?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What we're trying to say is that real powerful interventions around climate change may well come from people and areas who dont explicitly identify with climate change politics. They may take the shape instead of food riots, struggles against property developers, fuel poverty campaigns etc.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are two key points of intervention coming up. On 2 April the G20 are meeting in Londons Docklands. Therell be a &lt;a href=&quot;/en/2009/02/421421.html&quot;&gt;Climate Camp&lt;/a&gt; in the Square Mile in the City of London on 1 April. Then in December Copenhagen sees the United Nations Climate Change Conference (COP15). Theres a huge mobilisation underway amid an ongoing debate about what attitude we should adopt. Inside? Outside? One foot in? Its been given added significance because will be almost exactly 10 years since the WTO shutdown in Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before that, We Wont Pay for Their Crisis are having a &lt;a href=&quot;/en/regions/leedsbradford/2009/02/421938.html&quot;&gt;meeting&lt;/a&gt; on Saturday 28 February. Its called We are an image from the future and we will be picking up some of these themes and trying to relate them to recent events across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>ZNet - Obama &amp;amp; Israel-Palestine</title>
            <link>http://www.zmag.org/znet/viewArticle/20364</link>

            <description>&lt;div id=&quot;allContent&quot;&gt;&amp;#13;
				&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Barack Obama is recognized to be a person of acute intelligence, a legal scholar, careful with his choice of words. He deserves to be taken seriously - both what he says, and what he omits. Particularly significant is his first substantive statement on foreign affairs, on January 22, at the State Department, when introducing George Mitchell to serve as his special envoy for Middle East peace.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Mitchell is to focus his attention on the Israel-Palestine problem, in the wake of the recent US-Israeli invasion of Gaza. During the murderous assault, Obama remained silent apart from a few platitudes, because, he said, there is only one president - a fact that did not silence him on many other issues. His campaign did, however, repeat his statement that &quot;if missiles were falling where my two daughters sleep, I would do everything in order to stop that.&quot; He was referring to Israeli children, not the hundreds of Palestinian children being butchered by US arms, about whom he could not speak, because there was only one president.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;On January 22, however, the one president was Barack Obama, so he could speak freely about these matters - avoiding, however, the attack on Gaza, which had, conveniently, been called off just before the inauguration.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Obama's talk emphasized his commitment to a peaceful settlement. He left its contours vague, apart from one specific proposal: &quot;the Arab peace initiative,&quot; Obama said, &quot;contains constructive elements that could help advance these efforts.  Now is the time for Arab states to act on the initiative's promise by supporting the Palestinian government under President Abbas and Prime Minister Fayyad, taking steps towards normalizing relations with Israel, and by standing up to extremism that threatens us all.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Obama is not directly falsifying the Arab League proposal, but the carefully framed deceit is instructive.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;The Arab League peace proposal does indeed call for normalization of relations with Israel - &lt;i&gt;in the context&lt;/i&gt; - repeat, &lt;i&gt;in the context &lt;/i&gt;of a two-state settlement in terms of the longstanding international consensus, which the US and Israel have blocked for over 30 years, in international isolation, and still do. The core of the Arab League proposal, as Obama and his Mideast advisers know very well, is its call for a peaceful political settlement in these terms, which are well-known, and recognized to be the only basis for the peaceful settlement to which Obama professes to be committed. The omission of that crucial fact can hardly be accidental, and signals clearly that Obama envisions no departure from US rejectionism. His call for the Arab states to act on a corollary to their proposal, while the US ignores even the existence of its central content, which is the precondition for the corollary, surpasses cynicism.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;The most significant acts to undermine a peaceful settlement are the daily US-backed actions in the occupied territories, all recognized to be criminal: taking over valuable land and resources and constructing what the leading architect of the plan, Ariel Sharon, called &quot;Bantustans&quot; for Palestinians - an unfair comparison because the Bantustans were far more viable than the fragments left to Palestinians under Sharon's conception, now being realized. But the US and Israel even continue to oppose a political settlement in words, most recently in December 2008, when the US and Israel (and a few Pacific islands) voted against a UN resolution supporting &quot;the right of the Palestinian people to self-determination&quot; (passed 173 to 5, US-Israel opposed, with evasive pretexts).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Obama had not one word to say about the settlement and infrastructure developments in the West Bank, and the complex measures to control Palestinian existence, designed to undermine the prospects for a peaceful two-state settlement.   His silence is a grim refutation of his oratorical flourishes about how &quot;I will sustain an active commitment to seek two states living side by side in peace and security.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Also unmentioned is Israel's use of US arms in Gaza, in violation not only of international but also US law. Or Washington's shipment of new arms to Israel right at the peak of the US-Israeli attack, surely not unknown to Obama's Middle East advisers.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Obama was firm, however, that smuggling of arms to Gaza must be stopped. He endorses the agreement of Condoleeza Rice and Israeli foreign minister Tzipi Livni that the Egyptian-Gaza border must be closed - a remarkable exercise of imperial arrogance, as the &lt;i&gt;Financial Times&lt;/i&gt; observed: &quot;as they stood in Washington congratulating each other, both officials seemed oblivious to the fact that they were making a deal about an illegal trade on someone else's border - Egypt in this case. The next day, an Egyptian official described the memorandum as `fictional'.&quot; Egypt's objections were ignored.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Returning to Obama's reference to the &quot;constructive&quot; Arab League proposal, as the wording indicates, Obama persists in restricting support to the defeated party in the January 2006 election, the only free election in the Arab world, to which the US and Israel reacted, instantly and overtly, by severely punishing Palestinians for opposing the will of the masters. A minor technicality is that Abbas's term ran out on January 9, and that Fayyad was appointed without confirmation by the Palestinian parliament (many of them kidnapped and in Israeli prisons). &lt;i&gt;Ha'aretz &lt;/i&gt;describes Fayyad as &quot;a strange bird in Palestinian politics. On the one hand, he is the Palestinian politician most esteemed by Israel and the West.  However, on the other hand, he has no electoral power whatsoever in Gaza or the West Bank.&quot; The report also notes Fayyad's &quot;close relationship with the Israeli establishment,&quot; notably his friendship with Sharon's extremist adviser Dov Weiglass.  Though lacking popular support, he is regarded as competent and honest, not the norm in the US-backed political sectors.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Obama's insistence that only Abbas and Fayyad exist conforms to the consistent Western contempt for democracy unless it is under control.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Obama provided the usual reasons for ignoring the elected government led by Hamas. &quot;To be a genuine party to peace,&quot; Obama declared, &quot;the quartet [US, EU, Russia, UN] has made it clear that Hamas must meet clear conditions: recognize Israel's right to exist; renounce violence; and abide by past agreements.&quot; Unmentioned, also as usual, is the inconvenient fact that the US and Israel firmly reject all three conditions. In international isolation, they bar a two-state settlement including a Palestinian state; they of course do not renounce violence; and they reject the quartet's central proposal, the &quot;road map.&quot; Israel formally accepted it, but with 14 reservations that effectively eliminate its contents (tacitly backed by the US). It is the great merit of Jimmy Carter's &lt;i&gt;Palestine: Peace not Apartheid&lt;/i&gt;, to have brought these facts to public attention for the first time - and in the mainstream, the only time.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;It follows, by elementary reasoning, that neither the US nor Israel is a &quot;genuine party to peace.&quot; But that cannot be. It is not even a phrase in the English language.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;It is perhaps unfair to criticize Obama for this further exercise of cynicism, because it is close to universal, unlike his scrupulous evisceration of the core component of the Arab League proposal, which is his own novel contribution.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Also near universal are the standard references to Hamas: a terrorist organization, dedicated to the destruction of Israel (or maybe all Jews). Omitted are the inconvenient facts that the US-Israel are not only dedicated to the destruction of any viable Palestinian state, but are steadily implementing those policies. Or that unlike the two rejectionist states, Hamas has called for a two-state settlement in terms of the international consensus: publicly, repeatedly, explicitly.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; Obama began his remarks by saying: &quot;Let me be clear: America is committed to Israel's security. And we will always support Israel's right to defend itself against legitimate threats.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;There was nothing about the right of Palestinians to defend themselves against far more extreme threats, such as those occurring daily, with US support, in the occupied territories. But that again is the norm.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Also normal is the enunciation of the principle that Israel has the right to defend itself. That is correct, but vacuous: so does everyone. But in the context the cliche is worse than vacuous: it is more cynical deceit.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;The issue is not whether Israel has the right to defend itself, like everyone else, but whether it has the right to do so &lt;i&gt;by force&lt;/i&gt;. No one, including Obama, believes that states enjoy a general right to defend themselves by force: it is first necessary to demonstrate that there are no peaceful alternatives that can be tried. In this case, there surely are.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;A narrow alternative would be for Israel to abide by a cease-fire, for example, the cease-fire proposed by Hamas political leader Khaled Mishal a few days before Israel launched its attack on December 27. Mishal called for restoring the 2005 agreement. That agreement called for an end to violence and uninterrupted opening of the borders, along with an Israeli guarantee that goods and people could move freely between the two parts of occupied Palestine, the West Bank and the Gaza Strip. The agreement was rejected by the US and Israel a few months later, after the free election of January 2006 turned out &quot;the wrong way.&quot; There are many other highly relevant cases.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;The broader and more significant alternative would be for the US and Israel to abandon their extreme rejectionism, and join the rest of the world - including the Arab states and Hamas - in supporting a two-state settlement in accord with the international consensus. It should be noted that in the past 30 years there has been one departure from US-Israeli rejectionism: the negotiations at Taba in January 2001, which appeared to be close to a peaceful resolution when Israel prematurely called them off. It would not, then, be outlandish for Obama to agree to join the world, even within the framework of US policy, if he were interested in doing so.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;In short, Obama's forceful reiteration of Israel's right to defend itself is another exercise of cynical deceit - though, it must be admitted, not unique to him, but virtually universal.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;The deceit is particularly striking in this case because the occasion was the appointment of Mitchell as special envoy. Mitchell's primary achievement was his leading role in the peaceful settlement in northern Ireland. It called for an end to IRA terror and British violence. Implicit is the recognition that while Britain had the right to defend itself from terror, it had no right to do so &lt;i&gt;by force&lt;/i&gt;, because there was a peaceful alternative: recognition of the legitimate grievances of the Irish Catholic community that were the roots of IRA terror. When Britain adopted that sensible course, the terror ended. The implications for Mitchell's mission with regard to Israel-Palestine are so obvious that they need not be spelled out. And omission of them is, again, a striking indication of the commitment of the Obama administration to traditional US rejectionism and opposition to peace, except on its extremist terms.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Obama also praised Jordan for its &quot;constructive role in training Palestinian security forces and nurturing its relations with Israel&quot; - which contrasts strikingly with US-Israeli refusal to deal with the freely elected government of Palestine, while savagely punishing Palestinians for electing it with pretexts which, as noted, do not withstand a moment's scrutiny.   It is true that Jordan joined the US in arming and training Palestinian security forces, so that they could violently suppress any manifestation of support for the miserable victims of US-Israeli assault in Gaza, also arresting supporters of Hamas and the prominent journalist Khaled Amayreh, while organizing their own demonstrations in support of Abbas and Fatah, in which most participants &quot;were civil servants and school children who were instructed by the PA to attend the rally,&quot; according to the &lt;i&gt;Jerusalem Post.  &lt;/i&gt;Our kind of democracy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Obama made one further substantive comment: &quot;As part of a lasting cease-fire, Gaza's border crossings should be open to allow the flow of aid and commerce, with an appropriate monitoring regime...&quot; He did not, of course, mention that the US-Israel had rejected much the same agreement after the January 2006 election, and that Israel had never observed similar subsequent agreements on borders.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Also missing is any reaction to Israel's announcement that it rejected the cease-fire agreement, so that the prospects for it to be &quot;lasting&quot; are not auspicious. As reported at once in the press, &quot;Israeli Cabinet Minister Binyamin Ben-Eliezer, who takes part in security deliberations, told Army Radio on Thursday that Israel wouldn't let border crossings with Gaza reopen without a deal to free [Gilad] Schalit&quot; (AP, Jan 22); Israel to keep Gaza crossings closed...An official said the government planned to use the issue to bargain for the release of Gilad Shalit, the Israeli soldier held by the Islamist group since 2006 (&lt;i&gt;Financial Times&lt;/i&gt;, Jan. 23); &quot;Earlier this week, Israeli Foreign Minister Tzipi Livni said that progress on Corporal Shalit's release would be a precondition to opening up the border crossings that have been mostly closed since Hamas wrested control of Gaza from the West Bank-based Palestinian Authority in 2007&quot; (&lt;i&gt;Christian Science Monitor&lt;/i&gt;, Jan. 23); &quot;an Israeli official said there would be tough conditions for any lifting of the blockade, which he linked with the release of Gilad Shalit&quot; (&lt;i&gt;FT&lt;/i&gt;, Jan. 23); among many others.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Shalit's capture is a prominent issue in the West, another indication of Hamas's criminality. Whatever one thinks about it, it is uncontroversial that capture of a soldier of an attacking army is far less of a crime than kidnapping of civilians, exactly what Israeli forces did the day before the capture of Shalit, invading Gaza city and kidnapping two brothers, then spiriting them across the border where they disappeared into Israel's prison complex. Unlike the much lesser case of Shalit, that crime was virtually unreported and has been forgotten, along with Israel's regular practice for decades of kidnapping civilians in Lebanon and on the high seas and dispatching them to Israeli prisons, often held for many years as hostages. But the capture of Shalit bars a cease-fire.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Obama's State Department talk about the Middle East continued with &quot;the deteriorating situation in Afghanistan and Pakistan... the central front in our enduring struggle against terrorism and extremism.&quot; A few hours later, US planes attacked a remote village in Afghanistan, intending to kill a Taliban commander. &quot;Village elders, though, told provincial officials there were no Taliban in the area, which they described as a hamlet populated mainly by shepherds. Women and children were among the 22 dead, they said, according to Hamididan Abdul Rahmzai, the head of the provincial council&quot; (&lt;i&gt;LA Times&lt;/i&gt;, Jan. 24).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin: 0in 0in 0pt&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Verdana&quot;&gt;Afghan president Karzai's first message to Obama after he was elected in November was a plea to end the bombing of Afghan civilians, reiterated a few hours before Obama was sworn in. This was considered as significant as Karzai's call for a timetable for departure of US and other foreign forces. The rich and powerful have their &quot;responsibilities.&quot; Among them, the &lt;i&gt;New York Times&lt;/i&gt; reported, is to &quot;provide security&quot; in southern Afghanistan, where &quot;the insurgency is homegrown and self-sustaining.&quot; All familiar. From &lt;i&gt;Pravda&lt;/i&gt; in the 1980s, for example.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
			&lt;/div&gt;</description>

        </item>
        <item>
            <title>SchNEWS 664 - 30th January 2009 - Iceland Meltdown</title>
            <link>http://www.schnews.org.uk/archive/news6642.php</link>
            <description>&lt;div id=&quot;article&quot;&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../index.php&quot;&gt;Home&lt;/a&gt; | Friday 30th January 2009 | Issue 664&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;

&amp;#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;news664.htm&quot;&gt;Back to the Full Issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;
&amp;#13;
&lt;div id=&quot;article&quot;&gt;&amp;#13;
&amp;#13;
&lt;h3&gt;ICELAND MELTDOWN&lt;/h3&gt;&amp;#13;

&amp;#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;b&gt;The Icelandic people sensationally booted out their government on Monday&lt;/b&gt; (26th) after the country was left ravaged by the collapse of their privatised financial system last October. The Icelandic government has been under mounting pressure since late last year with thousands of people gathering outside parliament demanding that the government resign.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&amp;#13;
This quickly bloomed into weekly mass riots with cops being rushed to hospital and 14-hour noise demos eventually forcing the disgraced elite to flee. This is the first Government casualty of the global financial crisis.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&amp;#13;
On Tuesday, the Icelandic president Olafur Ragnar Grimsson called on Ingibjorg Gisladottir, leader of the Social Democratic Alliance party, to form a coalition with the Left-Green movement. Gisladottir - foreign minister in the previous government - has now appointed Johanna Sigurdardottir, the social affairs minister, as the interim prime minister until new elections are held in May. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&amp;#13;
Since the Icelandic conservative government came to power eighteen years ago it has followed seriously dumb ambitions that were way out of its economys league. It started off by handing over its three banks to government cronies, who in turn egged on the nation to borrow up to seven times its GDP - which eventually caused a complete financial meltdown (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.schnews.org.uk/archive/news657.htm&quot;&gt;SchNEWS 657&lt;/a&gt;). Iceland is looking more and more like (free market get rich quick capitalist theory) neo-liberalism gone bonkers in microcosm. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&amp;#13;
The case of Iceland also demonstrates the fact that it usually takes a full-on systematic collapse before people get it together and say enough is enough. Yesterdays IMF annual report predicted that the UK economy will soon take a 2.8% nose dive. On hearing about the UKs rough financial state one flushed Icelander exclaimed, The Brits should take a leaf out of our book and throw out their government! Now theres an idea. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&amp;#13;
* See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.savingiceland.org&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.savingiceland.org&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://aftaka.org/tag/english&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://aftaka.org/tag/english&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&amp;#13;
* Bjork is collaborating with Icelandic venture capital firm Audur Capital in a 100-million-krona (about 575,000) fund that seeks to boost Icelands ravaged economy by way of investing in green technology. SchNEWSs response has been an Oh So Quiet cynical for the chances of greener capitalism to save the day...&amp;#13;

&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;
&amp;#13;
&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;
&amp;#13;
&lt;div id=&quot;keywords&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:35%; margin-top:28px; border-top:1px solid #ddddbb; padding-top:8px&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Keywords:&lt;/b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;../keywordSearch/?keyword=direct+action&amp;amp;source=664&quot;&gt;direct action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;#13;

&amp;#13;
&amp;#13;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>ZNet - Education After Neoliberalism</title>
            <link>http://www.zmag.org/znet/viewArticle/20141</link>
            <description>&lt;div id=&quot;allContent&quot;&gt;&amp;#13;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;As the financial meltdown reaches historic proportions, free-market fundamentalism, or neoliberalism as it is called in some quarters, is losing both its claim to legitimacy and its claims on democracy. Once upon a time a perceived bastion of liberal democracy, the social state is being recalled from exile, as the decades-long conservative campaign against the alleged abuses of &quot;big government&quot; - its euphemism for a form of governance that assumed a measure of responsibility for the education, health and general welfare of its citizens - has been widely discredited. Not only have the starving and drowning efforts of the Right been revealed in all their malicious cruelty, but government is about to have a Cinderella moment; it is about to become &quot;cool,&quot; as Prince Charming-elect Barack Obama famously put it. The idea has enchanted many. The economist and recent Nobel laureate, Paul Krugman, has argued that the correct response to the current credit and financial crisis is to &quot;greatly expand the role of government to rescue an ailing economy,&quot; with the proviso that all new government programs must be devoid of even a hint of corruption.(1) Bob Herbert has called for more government regulation to offset the dark cloud of impoverishment that resulted from the last thirty years of deregulation, privatization and tax breaks for the wealthiest Americans.(2) And there are others, sophisticated thinkers all, such as Dean Baker, David Korten, Naomi Klein and Joseph E. Stiglitz, who have traced the roots of the current financial crisis to the adaptation of neoliberal economic policy, which fostered a grim alignment among the state, corporate capital and transnational corporations. Even New York Times op-ed writer Thomas Friedman has found a way to live comfortably with the idea. He wants to retool the country's educational mainframe, teaching young people to be more creative in their efforts to build &quot;the most productivity-enhancing infrastructure,&quot; - even as the stated goal unhappily recapitulates the neoliberal fantasy that unchecked growth cures all social ills.(3) And a contrite Alan Greenspan, erstwhile disciple of Ayn Rand, recently admitted before a Congressional committee that he may have made a mistake in assuming &quot;that enlightened self-interest alone would prevent bankers, mortgage brokers, investment bankers and others from gaming the system for their own personal financial benefit.&quot;(4)&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;With the exception of Greenspan and Friedman, all of these economists and intellectuals have rejected a market fundamentalism that: dismantled the historically guaranteed social provisions provided - however partially and imperfectly - by the welfare state; defined consumerism and profit-making as the essence of democratic citizenship, and equated freedom with the unrestricted ability of markets to govern economic relations free of government regulation. In doing so, they have repudiated the neoliberal dystopian vision that there are no alternatives to a market-driven society, which adhered to the inviolability and inevitability of economic law. And they have condemned a market rationality that advanced private interests as it sold off public goods and services, that sought to invest only in corporate and private sectors as it starved the social. The neoliberal mantra that There Is No Alternative has been replaced by a new, equally insistent and increasingly pervasive call for reform and regulation. With the evils of a neoliberal &quot;voodoo&quot; economics exposed at long last, we can look forward to the dawn of a new democratic age.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Unfortunately, what so many writers and scholars have taken for granted in their thoughtful criticisms of neoliberalism and their calls for immediate economic reform is the presupposition that we have on hand and in stock generations of young people and adults who have somehow been schooled for the last several decades in an entirely different set of values and cultural attitudes, who do not equate the virtue of reason with an ethically truncated instrumental rationality, who know alternative sets of social relations that are irreducible to the rolls of buyer and seller, and who are not only intellectually prepared but morally committed to the staggering challenges that comprehensive reform requires. This is where the fairy tale ending to an era of obscene injustice careens headlong into reality. Missing from the roadmaps that lead us back out of Alice's rabbit hole, back out of a distorted world where reason and judgment don't apply, is precisely the necessity to understand the success of neoliberalism as a pervasive political and educational force, a pedagogy and form of governance that couples &quot;forms of knowledge, strategies of power and technologies of self.&quot;(5) Neoliberalism not only transformed economic agendas throughout the overdeveloped world, it transformed politics, restructured social relations, produced an array of reality narratives (not unlike reality TV) and disciplinary measures that normalized its perverted view of citizenship, the state and the supremacy of market relations. In the concerted effort to reverse course, dare one not take account of the profound emotional appeal, let alone ideological hold, of neoliberalism on the American public? The success of a market ideology that has produced shocking levels of inequality and impoverishment and a market morality that has spawned rapacious greed and corruption should raise fundamental questions. How did market rule prove capable of enlisting in such a compelling way the consent of the vast majority of Americans, who cast themselves, no less, in the role of the &quot;moral majority?&quot; The refusal of such an analysis, framed nonetheless as a response, by many theorists (including many leftists) typically explains that working people &quot;do not, under normal circumstances, care deeply about anything beyond the size of their paychecks.&quot;(6) But this is too quick, and far too inadequate. We argue that matters of popular consciousness, public sentiment and individual and social agency are far too important as part of a larger political and educational struggle not be taken seriously by those who advocate the long and difficult project of democratic reform.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Tragically, few intellectuals providing critical commentary on the financial and credit crisis offer any insights regarding how the educational force of the culture actually works pedagogically to reproduce neoliberal ideology, values, identifications and consent. How exactly is it possible to imagine a more just, more equitable transformation in government and economics without a simultaneous transformation in culture, consciousness, social identities and values? We are not implying a vulgar economism is at work in such commentaries in our new and sophisticated information age, but there is a tendency to undertheorize the important relationship between the production of neoliberal economics, popular consent, cultural politics and pedagogy. In doing so, the primacy of the force and influence of formal and informal educational sites, or the apparatuses of what we call public pedagogy, which have mediated the ever-shifting and dynamic modes of common sense for the past several decades remains invisible and so unchecked. Yet the formation of this common sense, which nonetheless served to legitimate the institutional arrangements of a rapacious capitalism, shifting class formations and colorblinding racial logics, has emerged alongside a number of significant and unsettling cultural transformations, to name a few of the most phenomenal: the now much-discussed culture of fear; the hyperindividualization and isolation of expanding consumer society; the ideology of privatization and the dissolution of social totality (and with visions of the good society); and the creation of the punishing state organized around the criminalization of social problems.(7) Indeed, the current focus on the rationality of exchange and exploitation does not capture the fate of those populations - refugees, jobless youth, the poor, immigrants, black and Latino communities - who came to exemplify all that was allegedly wrong with social safety nets that produced pathological forms of dependency, who were often the unwitting targets of the war on crime and the war on terror, as it played out on the domestic front. These, moreover, are populations increasingly rendered disposable not only because they exist outside any productive notion of what it means to be a citizen-consumer, but because of a decades-long racist campaign that invented cultural deficits and deficiencies raising the specter of contagion and threat. The questions we need to be asking ourselves extend beyond how we proceed with competent and effective economic reform. There is a neoliberal logic that extends beyond the economic. We must also consider how we dismantle the culture of fear, how we learn to think beyond the narrow dictates of instrumental rationalities, how we decriminialize certain identities, how we depathologize the concept of dependency and recognize it as our common fate, how we reclaim the public good, how we reconstitute, in short, a viable and sustainable democratic society.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Does it not seem odd, for example, that we bemoan the lack of a culture of service among young college graduates and at the same time seek to improve an educational system by implementing school policy that financially rewards students for scholastic achievement? Is it not a bit naive to assume that such policy can end in any other way than a &quot;pay to play&quot; mentality? We must surely reform our financial institutions and our economic philosophies more generally, but so too must we reform those institutions, professional competencies, and social identities altered by decades of neoliberal rule. And that will prove a most challenging endeavor. It will require that universities, news media, hospitals and clinics, schools and other institutions return critical and reflexive decision-making capacities to professors, journalists, doctors, nurses, teachers and others and away from accountants and middle managers. It means that the bottom line will not determine curricula or shape research agendas; it will not drive the news media, determine a course of medical treatment or fix the outcome of clinical trials. Once-trusted relations between doctors and patients, teachers and students, parents and children will no longer suffer the flatting out of their respective rolls to that of buyer and seller.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;In spite of the crucial connection between various modes of domination and pedagogy, there is little input from progressive social theorists of what it might mean to theorize how education as a form of cultural politics actually constructs particular modes of address, identification, affective investments and social relations that produce consent and complicity with the ethos and practice of neoliberalism. Hence, while the current economic crisis has called into question the economic viability of neoliberal values and policies, it often does so by implying that neoliberal rationality can be explained through an economic optic alone, and consequently gives the relationship of politics, culture and inequality scant analysis. Neoliberal rationality is lived and legitimated in relation to the intertwining of culture, politics and meaning. Any viable challenge to the culture of neoliberalism as well as the current economic crisis it has generated must address not merely the diffuse operations of power throughout civil society and the globe, but also what it means to engage those diverse educational sites producing and legitimating neoliberal common sense, whether they be newspapers, advertising, the Internet, television or more recent spheres developed as part of the new information revolution. In addition, it is crucial to examine what role public intellectuals, think tanks, the media and universities actually play pedagogically in constructing and legitimating neoliberal world views, and how the latter works pedagogically in producing neoliberal subjects and securing consent.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Politics is not simply about the production and protection of economic formations; it is also about the production of individuals, desires, identifications, values and modes of understanding for inhabiting the ideological and institutional forms that make up a social order. At the very least, any attempt to both understand the current crisis and what it would mean to produce a new kind of subject willing to invest in and struggle for a democratic society needs to raise another set of questions in addition to those currently posed. For example: What educational challenges would have to be addressed in overcoming the deeply felt view in American culture that criticism is destructive, or for that matter a deeply rooted anti-intellectualism reinforced daily through various forms of public pedagogical address made available by talk radio and the televisual infotainment sectors?[7] How might we engage pedagogical practices that open up a culture of questioning that enables people to resist and reject neoliberal assumptions that decouples private woes from public considerations, reduces citizenship to consumerism and makes free-market ideology coterminous with democracy? What are the implications of theorizing education, pedagogy and the practice of learning as essential to social change and where might such interventions take place? How might it be possible to theorize the pedagogical importance of the new media and the new modes of political literacy and cultural production they employ, or to analyze the circuits of power, translation and distribution that make up neoliberalism's vast pedagogical apparatus - extending from talk radio and screen culture to the Internet and newspapers? At stake here is both recognizing the importance of the media as a site of public pedagogy and breaking the monopoly of information, which is a central pillar of neoliberal common sense. These are only some of the questions that would be central to any viable recognition of what it would mean to theorize education as a condition that enables both critique, understood as more than the struggle against incomprehension, and social responsibility as the foundation for forms of intervention that are oppositional and empowering. To imagine a simpler solution is to be sold on a fairy tale.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;(1). Paul Krugman, &quot;Barack Be Good,&quot; New York Times (December 26, 2008), p. A25.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;(2). Bob Herbert, &quot;Stop Being Stupid,&quot; New York Times (December 27, 2008), p. A19.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;(3). Thomas L. Friedman, &quot;Time to Reboot America,&quot; New York Times (December 24, 2008), p. A21.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;(4). Deborah Jones Barrow, &quot;Greenspan Shrugged? Did Any Rand Cause Our Financial Crisis?&quot; WowOwow (October 24, 2008). Online: &lt;/font&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wowowow.com/post/greenspan-shrugged-did-ayn-rand-cause-our-financial-crisis-128286&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;http://www.wowowow.com/post/greenspan-shrugged-did-ayn-rand-cause-our-financial-crisis-128286&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;(5).Thomas Lemke, &quot;Foucault, Governmentality, and Critique,&quot; Paper presented at the Rethinking Marxism Conference, University of Amherst (MA), September 21-24, 2000, Online: &lt;/font&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thomaslemkeweb.de/publikationen/Foucault,%20Governmentality,%20and%20Critique%20IV-2.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;http://www.thomaslemkeweb.de/publikationen/Foucault,%20Governmentality,%20and%20Critique%20IV-2.pdf&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;(6). Ellen Willis, &quot;Escape from Freedom: What's the Matter with Tom Frank (and the Lefties who Love Him)?&quot; Situations 1:2 (2006), p. 9.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;(7). This issue is taken up in great detail in Henry A. Giroux, Youth in a Suspect Society: Democracy or Disposability? (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2009).&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Henry A. Giroux holds the Global TV Network chair in English and Cultural Studies at McMaster University in Canada. His most recent books include: &quot;Take Back Higher Education&quot; (co-authored with Susan Searls Giroux, 2006), &quot;The University in Chains: Confronting the Military-Industrial-Academic Complex&quot; (2007) and &quot;Against the Terror of Neoliberalism: Politics Beyond the Age of Greed&quot; (2008). His newest book, &quot;Youth in a Suspect Society: Democracy or Disposability?&quot; will be published by Palgrave Macmillan in 2009.&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Susan Searls Giroux is an Associate Professor of English and Cultural Studies at McMaster University. Here most recent books include &quot;The Theory Toolbox&quot; (co-authored with Jeff Nealon, 2004) and &quot;Take Back Higher Education&quot; (co-authored with Henry A. Giroux, 2006).&quot;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;#13;
			&lt;/div&gt;</description>

        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
